# Jiarui Fang (方佳瑞)

 $\leftarrow$  +(86) 13717819702

• https://github.com/feifeibear

✓ fangjiarui123@gmail.com Update Date: July 20, 2022

Extensive research and engineering experience in developing high-performance computing systems. Core contributor to a variety of open-source software that have earned over **6k stars** on GitHub. First author of publications on top-tier system conferences.

# **Work Experience**

• HPC-AI TECH, a startup Co-founder Engineer, Tech Manager

Beijing, China February 2022 - Now

• WeChat, Tencent Senior Software Engineer (T11) at WeChat AI

Beijing, China July 2019 - February 2022

Mentor: Dr. Jie Zhou

• National Supercomputing Center in Wuxi Ph.D Research Intern at R&D Center

Wuxi, Jiangsu, China August 2017 - May 2019

Mentor: Prof. Haohuan Fu

# **Education**

• Tsinghua University

Beijing, China

July 2019

**Ph.D.** in Department of Computer Science & Technology

Advisor: Prof. Guangwen Yang, Co-advisor: Prof. Haohuan Fu

Dissertation: Parallel Deep Learning Training System on on Sunway TaihuLight [pdf]

• University of California, Davis

Davis, CA, USA

Visiting Scholar in Department of Computer Science Engineering August 2017 - August 2018 Advisor: Assistant Prof. Cho-Jui Hsieh [link]

• Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications **B.S.** in Department of Computer Science & Technology

Beijing, China June 2014

Ranking 6<sup>th</sup> top 2% among 300 students (Honored 2014 Outstanding Graduate of Beijing)

# **Project Highlights**

• Building Large-scale Deep Learning Framework for Big Model Area

HPC-AI Tech

February 2022 - Now

I am the manager of a 10+ member tech team building next-generation open-sourced AI Infra. Besides several on-going projects, our Open-source projects include:

- 1. Colossal-AI [link] is a Unified Deep Learning System for Large-Scale Parallel Training.
- 2. Energon-AI [link] is a Large-scale Model Inference System.
- Building Open-sourced Deep Learning Infrastructures

Wechat AI, Tencent

July 2019 - February 2022 I

was dedicated to solving real production problems in Tencent by proposing innovative system

1. I initialized and developed **TurboTransformers** [link], a fast runtime for transformer inference on CPU and GPU.

- 2. I initialized and developed **PatrickStar** [link], Parallel Training of Large Language Models via a Dynamic Chunk-based Memory Management.
- 3. Both software is open-sourced on Tencent's official Github and has brought significant cost savings for the company's billion Daily Active User products. I was awarded as the Excellent Contributor for Open-sourced Collaboration of 2021 by Tencent, which is the **highly-valued personal prize** of the company. There are extensive Chinese media reports on my open-source achievements [link], [link].

## • Building Deep Basic Modules for WeChat App

Wechat AI, Tencent

July 2019 - March 2021

I contributed to a set of basic modules in the WeChat App, including The WeChat Input Engine, the WeChat Open Dialogue Platform, and the WeChat Translation System. WeChat is a super App with over 1 Billion active users per month.

# • Large-scale Deep Learning Training (DL) System for GPU Supercomputer

University of California, Davis

September 2017 - August 2018

I designed the RedSync – a distributed data-parallel Deep Learning training system using gradient pruning and quantization. When scaled up to 128 GPUs, the RedSync brought significant performance improvements to DNNs previously considered hard to scale.

## • High Performance Deep Learning System for the Sunway TaihuLight

National Supercomputing Center in Wuxi

April 2016 - August 2019 I

built a deep learning framework from scratch on the Sunway TaihuLight, which is based on the innovative SW26010 many-core processors and ranked **No.1** on the 47th-50th Top500 Supercomputer lists.

- 1. I designed the swGEMM a GEneral Matrix Multiplication (GEMM) library based on SW26010. Core code is handwritten by the assembly code, reaching 97% of peak performance. Significant speedups (2-10x) were achieved by applying swGEMM instead of default BLAS to deep learning applications.
- 2. Designed the swDNN a library that provides APIs for mainstream DL operator (CONV, LSTM, FC, BN, and activations). Regarding the most complicated CONV ops, three parallel schemes were designed for the special SW26010 many-core architecture, i.e. explicit GEMM, implicit GEMM, and Winograd. The computing efficiency of swDNN exceeded cuDNNv7.5 running on Tesla K40.
- 3. I designed the swATOP an end-to-end automated framework that optimizes complex parallel DL operator code on SW26010. By reading several lines of DSL statements, swATOP can automatically generate code that exceeds manual optimization performance.
- 4. I designed the swCaffe an MPI-based deep learning framework on the Sunway TaihuLight. Synchronization employed an innovative topology-aware MPI Allreduce method which is 10x faster than the default MPI\_Allreduce on 1024 nodes.

## • High Performance Scientific Computing Applications

Department of Earth System Science, Tsinghua University

February 2014 - March 2016

- 1. I proposed a generalized cache-friendly design based on NVIDIA GPUs and Intel Xeon Phis for complex spatially-variable coefficient (CSVC) stencils. Gained 4x speedup in the seismic imaging software (GeoEast-Lightning) used by China National Petroleum Corporation.
- 2. I accelerated a series of scientific applications on different HPC platforms, including transient electromagnetic simulation on CPU cluster; remote sensing data analysis with SVM on Intel Xeon Phi; Community Earth System Model (CESM), and crop modeling on Sunway TaihuLight.

- Jiarui Fang, Yang Yu, Zilin Zhu, Shenggui Li, Yang You, Jie Zhou, PatrickStar: Parallel Training of Pre-trained Models via Chunk-based Memory Management, Preprint on arXive. [pdf].
- Jiarui Fang, Yang Yu, Chengduo. Zhao, Jie Zhou, TurboTransformers: An Efficient GPU Serving System For Transformer Models, Proceedings of the 26th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel (PPoPP 2021). [pdf].
- Jiarui Fang, Haohuan Fu, Guangwen Yang, Cho-Jui Hsieh, RedSync: Reducing Synchronization Traffic for Distributed Deep Learning. Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing (JPDC), Volume 133, November 2019, Pages 30-39. [arXiv][pdf].
- Wei Gao\*, Jiarui Fang\*, Wenlai Zhao, Jinzhe Yang, Long Wang, Lin Gan, Haohuan Fu, Guangwen Yang. swATOP: Automatically Optimizing Deep Learning Operators on SW26010 Many-Core Processor. Proceedings of the 48th International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP), 2019. (\* equal contribution) [pdf].
- Jiarui Fang\*, and Li, Liandeng\* and Fu, Haohuan and Jiang, Jinlei and Zhao, Wenlai and He, Conghui and You, Xin and Yang, Guangwen. swCaffe: a Parallel Framework for Accelerating Deep Learning Applications on Sunway TaihuLight, IEEE Cluster (Cluster), Belfast, UK, 2018. [pdf]. (\* equal contribution).
- Jiarui Fang, Haohuan Fu, Wenlai Zhao, Bingwei Chen, Weijie Zheng, and Guangwen Yang. swDNN: A library for Accelerating Deep Learning Applications on Sunway Taihulight. In Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS), 2017 IEEE International, pages 615–624. IEEE, 2017. [pdf]
- Jiarui Fang,, Haohuan Fu, Guangwen Yang. Cache-friendly Design for Complex Spatially-variable Coefficient Stencils on Many-core Architectures. IEEE 23rd International Conference on High Performance Computing, Data, and Analytics (HiPC),p222-p231, Hyderabad, India, 2016. [pdf]
- Jiarui Fang, Haohuan Fu, He Zhang, Wei Wu, Nanxun Dai, Lin Gan, Guangwen Yang.

  Optimizing Complex Spatially-Variant Coefficient Stencils for Seismic Modeling on

  GPU. IEEE 21st International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS),
  p641-p648 Melbourne, Australia, 2015. [pdf]
- Jiarui Fang, Haohuan Fu, Guangwen Yang, Wei Wu, Nanxun Dai. **GPU-based explicit time** evolution method. The 84th Society of Exploration Geophysicists Technical Program Expanded Abstracts (SEG), p3549-p3553, New Orleans, USA, 2015 [pdf]

#### Skills

- Good at English: GRE 322 (Verbal 153, October 2012)
- Programing Language: C/C++, CUDA, Python
- **Technical Skills:** Computer Architecture, Parallel Computing, Software Performance Tuning and Optimization, Deep Learning, Numerical Computing.

#### **Academia Service**

• I serve as the reviewer of journals include ACM Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization (TACO), Parallel Computing (PARCO), Transactions on Cloud Computing (TOCC), Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS).

#### References

• Jie Zhou

Director of the Pattern Recognition Center, WeChat AI. Email:withtomzhou@tencent.com

## • Guangwen Yang

Professor in Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University, Director of the National Supercomputing Center in Wuxi. Email:ygw@tsinghua.edu.cn

# • Haohuan Fu

Professor in Department of Earth Science, Tsinghua University, Deputy Director of the National Supercomputing Center in Wuxi. Email:haohuan@tsinghua.edu.cn

#### • Cho-Jui Hsieh

Assistant Professor in Department of Computer Science, University of California, Los Angeles. Email:chohsieh@cs.ucla.edu